<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd upon St. Matthew's Day, 1699 before the right honourable the Lord Mayor and the right worshipful and worshipful the governors of all the city-hospitals at Christ-Church, London / by Thomas Staynoe.</title>
            <author>Staynoe, Thomas, d. 1708.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61368</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5355</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34598</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14516916</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14516916</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102500</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61368)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102500)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1071:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd upon St. Matthew's Day, 1699 before the right honourable the Lord Mayor and the right worshipful and worshipful the governors of all the city-hospitals at Christ-Church, London / by Thomas Staynoe.</title>
                  <author>Staynoe, Thomas, d. 1708.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benj. Tooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCIX [1699]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXLV, 9 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:102500:1"/>
            <p>CHILD Mayor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jovis quinto die Octobris,</hi> 1699. <hi>Annoque Regni Regis</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>helmi <hi>Tertii,</hi> Angliae, <hi>&amp;c. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndecimo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THIS Court doth deſire Mr. <hi>Staynoe</hi> to Print his Sermon Preach'd at <hi>Chriſt</hi>-Church on St. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Day laſt, before the Lord-Mayor, Aldermen, and the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the ſeveral Hoſpitals of this City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>GOODFELLOW.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102500:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd upon St. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Day, 1699. Before the Right Honourable the LORD MAYOR, AND THE Right Worſhipful and Worſhipful the GOVERNORS of all the CITY-HOSPITALS, AT Chriſt-Church, <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS STAYNOE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Benj. Tooke</hi> at the <hi>Middle-Temple-Gate</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> MDCXCIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:102500:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102500:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſalm 145.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The Lord is good to all; and his tender mercies are over all his Works.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Pſalmiſt in the Text does expreſly Aſſert and Diſplay Gods goodneſs and tender Mercies to all his Creatures: Which Our Saviour inlarges and improves, when he bids us behold the Fowls of the Air; which though they Sow not, neither do they Reap, nor gather into Barns, yet are Fed by our Heavenly Father; And then by putting the Queſtion, Are ye not much better than they? does ſtrongly imply, that he will do at leaſt as much for the ſupply of the wants and neceſſities of <hi>Men:</hi> with more to the ſame purpoſe, which you may find in the 6th. <hi>chap.</hi> of St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> and in ſeveral other places, which we need not reckon up.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:102500:3"/>
            <p> For it is ſufficient for our preſent deſign (and we have ſufficient ground for ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign from our <hi>Text</hi>) to make it good, that God has <hi>taken</hi> care of, and made ſufficient Proviſion for the Support and Maintenance of <hi>all</hi> Men in the World, and particularly of the <hi>Poor</hi> and <hi>Needy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In order to which we take notice in the Firſt Place, and in General, That God hath given the Earth to the Children of Men; and that we all ſtand bound to make good ſuch his Donation in the full extent and latitude of it: which is, that all the ſons of Men, to whom the gift is made, may be partakers of ſuch gifts. For your more full and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive underſtanding of which, I would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you to take notice of theſe following Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That God has given the Earth, that is the Uſe, Product, Fruits, and Profits of it to the Children of Men. This appears (Firſt) by matter of fact, becauſe we find Man (who is the Creature of God as well as the Earth is ſo) in the actual poſſeſſion of ſuch Earth; and becauſe we alſo find him endowed with ſuch Powers and Faculties, that all other things, which the Earth does produce, are
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102500:3"/>in ſubjection to him, and at his diſpoſal. By which as it appears, that Man is the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and in actual poſſeſſion of the Earth; So, if it be but granted, that the Earth is the Lords and the fulneſs thereof (which we ſhall at preſent take for granted, becauſe we take it for granted that he made it) then the Concluſion is Eaſy and Natural, That Man's poſſeſſion of the Earth, and his Right and Title to ſuch poſſeſſion, comes from God, and that therefore God gave the Earth to Man.</p>
            <p>But if we ſhould fail in ſuch our way of Reaſoning; yet we have a more full confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of this Point, and that too by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Deed of Gift made to Man by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, when he bids him be Fruitful and Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply, and repleniſh the Earth, and ſubdue it; <hi>And have dominion over the fiſh of the ſea, and over the fowl of the air, and over every living thing, that moveth upon the earth;</hi> with more to the ſame purpoſe recorded in the beginning of <hi>Geneſis.</hi> And purſuant hereunto the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> tells us, in the 115. <hi>Pſal.</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 16. That <hi>God hath given the earth to the children of men.</hi> Now a Deed of Gift from God, and that recorded by God himſelf, muſt needs be good; and therefore without any more to do, we ſhall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102500:4"/>conclude in general, That God gave the Earth, that is, (as we ſaid before) the Uſe, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, Fruits and Profits of it, to Man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I would have you conſider, that when God gave the Earth to Man, he did not give it to this Man, or to that Man, excluſive of all the reſt; but that he gave it to Mankind in general, and that by ſo doing he gave it to every Man whom he ſhould at any time make to dwell upon the face of it. And this is notorious, becauſe he has Created every particular Man with ſuch natural wants which muſt be ſupplied from the Earth; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he has furniſhed the Earth with ſuch a quantity of Proviſions, as are abundantly ſufficient for all the Men in it. Now, where the <hi>Wants</hi> of all are Created by <hi>Him,</hi> who Creates the <hi>Supplies;</hi> and where the <hi>Supplies</hi> are ſufficient to <hi>anſwer</hi> to ſuch Wants; there the bare <hi>donation</hi> of ſuch Supplies is a ſufficient Argument of the <hi>extent</hi> of ſuch Donation: that is, it proves, that ſuch Donation was deſigned and intended to all. There is therefore no doubt, but that every Man in the Earth has a Right and Title to ſo much of the Fruits and Products of it, as may be ſufficient for the ſupply of his Natural Wants, and that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102500:4"/>too by the tenor of that general Charter by which God gave the Earth to the Children of Men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> God has by the Inabilities and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointments, or Providential defeats of many Men, put it out of their power to gain to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the <hi>Poſſeſſion</hi> of ſuch their Right and Title before they have it; or to <hi>recover</hi> ſuch their Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion when they have <hi>loſt</hi> it. For though he has in general given every Man a <hi>Right</hi> to ſo much as his Natural Wants <hi>require;</hi> yet he has not by any particular Aſſignment <hi>allotted</hi> to every Man ſuch a <hi>ſeparate</hi> Portion of thoſe things which ſhall <hi>Anſwer</hi> to ſuch Wants; but has left ſuch diviſion to be made by every Man's Wit, Parts, Power, or Induſtry, by Humane Laws, or by his own particular and over-ruling Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences. By which perhaps it may ſeem at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, that his general Grant, as to ſuch Men, is of no Uſe or Benefit. For what benefit can it be to any Man, that he has a <hi>Right</hi> to have his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Wants <hi>ſupplied,</hi> when by reaſon of Inabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Diſappointments or Providential Defeats, he cannot obtain the <hi>actual Poſſeſſion</hi> of ſuch his Right, and ſo his Wants are ſtill <hi>continued?</hi> I would deſire you therefore to conſider in the</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourth</hi> Place, That God to make good his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Donation in the full Extent and Latitude
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102500:5"/>of it, that is, ſo that it may reach the Caſe of every <hi>particular</hi> Man, has ordained his Law of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Charity.</hi> Now by ſuch his Law his Wiſdom has ſo contrived things, that thoſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Wants of any particular Men, that cannot be ſupplied by <hi>themſelves,</hi> ſhall be ſupplied by <hi>others;</hi> and ſo what we do not receive immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately from the <hi>Fountain,</hi> we ſhall derive from the <hi>Stream.</hi> And though things may to inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate People ſeem to have been better ordered, had God in the diviſion of the Fruits and Profits of the Earth allotted to every particular Man the Poſſeſſion of his <hi>own</hi> Portion, and ſo had put his neceſſary Proviſions and Supplies in his <hi>own</hi> Hand, and by conſequence in his own Power: Yet it muſt be confeſſed, that ſuch an Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation comes from a ſhort-ſightedneſs in the Wiſdom of the Divine Providence; becauſe it is Notorious, that that Wiſdom has by ſuch an unequal diſtribution of the good things of this World ſo ordered Affairs, as to provide, that <hi>Goodneſs, Mercy,</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> may be mixed with the <hi>Plenty</hi> of thoſe that abound; and that <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, Humility,</hi> and <hi>Patience,</hi> may be mixed with the <hi>Poverty</hi> of thoſe that want; and that by that means he has made proviſion for the <hi>Souls,</hi> as well as the <hi>Bodies</hi> of <hi>both.</hi> And it muſt be confeſſed ſtill further, that ſuch a comprehenſive
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102500:5"/>proviſion is worthy the <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Bounty</hi> of a God, and (when things are rightly conſidered) of his Wiſdom too. For from this unequal di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution of his Bleſſings ariſes that Regular and Beautiful Subordination in Mankind, from which all <hi>Governments</hi> whatſoever, and all the <hi>Bleſſings</hi> of ſuch Governments do flow: And ſo, what Inconſiderate men may <hi>think</hi> an <hi>Hardſhip</hi> to <hi>ſome,</hi> a prudent examination of the matter will <hi>pronounce</hi> to be a <hi>Bleſſing</hi> to <hi>all,</hi> becauſe an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Harmony is the happy Reſult of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Varieties and Inequalities.</p>
            <p>And what is thus true of the unequal diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Wealth</hi> among the Children of Men, will be found to be ſo alſo of all <hi>other</hi> the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal Diſtributions of any <hi>other</hi> Endowments that come from the Supreme and Univerſal Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor. For though he may give more Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, or more Power, or more Favour and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to one Man than to another; yet his Law of Love and Charity makes a good compenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ſuch Inequality; becauſe by that Law he requires and expects, as he gives ſuch Bleſſings <hi>only</hi> to <hi>ſome</hi> men, ſo that they ſhould <hi>communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate ſome</hi> of the Advantages of them, to <hi>others;</hi> and that by ſuch <hi>Communications</hi> a Mutual Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and Friendly Correſpondence, and all the Bleſſings of ſuch Correſpondence and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102500:6"/>ſhould be maintained among Mankind.</p>
            <p>Now in order to bring what we have hitherto offered, to our preſent purpoſe and deſign, I would firſt take notice, That as all thoſe things in which our <hi>Wealth does</hi> or <hi>can</hi> conſiſt, are confeſſedly made by God (for to a ſober and underſtanding Conſideration, all the <hi>Productions</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> are the <hi>effects</hi> of <hi>Omnipotence</hi>) ſo all our <hi>Perſonal</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, Powers and Faculties, by which we obtain Power and Intereſt, or are enabled for any other Uſeful and Beneficial purpoſes, do come from God alſo. For it is certain, that we can no more make our own <hi>Powers</hi> and <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties,</hi> than we can make Our <hi>ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Remark then being left in the way to make clear and plain what is to follow, we do to our preſent purpoſe and main deſign lay it down in the Firſt place, That every Man is in Juſtice and Equity bound by the bare <hi>acceptance</hi> of any <hi>Donation</hi> whatſoever, to make good thoſe <hi>Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> upon which ſuch Donation is made. For the Conditions being ſo annexed to the Deed of Gift, as to be made a part of it; it is not left in his power to <hi>accept</hi> the one, and <hi>refuſe</hi> the <hi>other.</hi> And therefore in all ſuch caſes, if he do not accept the Conditions with the Deed, it is as good as taken for granted by the common ſenſe of Mankind, that he does refuſe the Deed likewiſe, and ſo the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102500:6"/>Deed does of it ſelf become Void and Null. When therefore God has <hi>Inriched</hi> any Man with the bounties of <hi>Nature,</hi> or <hi>Endowed</hi> his <hi>Perſon</hi> with the <hi>Gifts</hi> of <hi>Nature;</hi> If he has by the Law of Love and Charity acquainted him, (as moſt certainly ſo he has) that he has not beſtowed theſe things upon him for his <hi>own</hi> ſake alone, but that he expects from him, that by them he ſhall be Beneficial to <hi>others</hi> alſo; Such a Law ſo limiting the Donation, does thereby become a Condition of ſuch Donation, and therefore to <hi>accept</hi> ſuch <hi>Donation,</hi> and yet to <hi>refuſe</hi> the <hi>Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance</hi> of the <hi>Condition,</hi> is Baſe, Ingrateful, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt. For with what Face can any Man accept all he has from God, and yet refuſe his Obedience to God's <hi>Commands,</hi> which requires him out of that All to ſupply his Brothers neceſſary Wants? And how devoid muſt he be both of Gratitude and Juſtice, who when God beſtows upon him Ten Thouſand Talents, will not, when God requires it, relieve his Brother with an Hundred Pence? Or how can any Man anſwer it to his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and Natural Modeſty (for all Men have ſome Modeſty from Nature, if they themſelves do not throw it off) to deny to do a ſmall Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to another at the ſollicitation of that Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor from whom alone he has received his Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance? Such a Denial is a flat Contradiction to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102500:7"/>all <hi>Gratitude,</hi> as it relates to ſuch his <hi>Benefactor;</hi> as it is a flat Contradiction to all <hi>Humanity,</hi> as it relates to his <hi>Wanting Neighbour.</hi> For God by his Law of Love and Charity does require us to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply other Peoples Wants, <hi>chiefly</hi> and <hi>moſtly</hi> out of our <hi>Superfluities;</hi> very <hi>ſeldom,</hi> and but in <hi>few</hi> Caſes, out of our <hi>Conveniencies;</hi> but in <hi>no</hi> Caſe whatſoever, out of our <hi>Neceſſities;</hi> In ſuch Caſes he leaves us to the Gratification of our Self-love, and permits us to prefer our ſelves. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the baſeneſs of Uncharitableneſs is always at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with this ugly Circumſtance, That we will not comply with our God, that is, with our Greateſt, nay our only Benefactor, in ſuch Caſes in which our Compliance can be no poſſible Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to our own Intereſt. By which it noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly appears, That as not to Comply with our God, even becauſe he is our <hi>God,</hi> is in the Caſe of Uncharitableneſs, <hi>Irreligion;</hi> and as not to comply with him, becauſe he is our <hi>Benefactor,</hi> is in the ſame Caſe <hi>Ingratitude;</hi> So, not to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with him, in the ſame Caſe ſtill, when it is <hi>no</hi> Prejudice to our Intereſt (as we have in ſhort ſhewed it cannot poſſibly be) is <hi>Folly.</hi> And he, who by his Uncharitableneſs can be content to Brand himſelf with Three ſuch Infamous Marks, may well be thought, as to have no Regard for <hi>God,</hi> or his <hi>Neighbour;</hi> ſo alſo to have no Regard to his own <hi>Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:102500:7"/>
            <p> But further, to perſwade you to Love and Charity from the Conſideration we are at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent upon; that is, as it has Regard to God, our great Benefactor: I do add, in the</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Second</hi> place, That as every Man is in Juſtice and Equity bound by the bare acceptance of any Donation to make good thoſe Conditions upon which the Donation was made; ſo every Man is bound, and that more <hi>ſtrongly,</hi> not to employ any part of the Donation <hi>againſt</hi> the Donor himſelf.</p>
            <p>This I therefore add, becauſe it will by and by appear, That where Men will not beſtow their ſuperfluities for the <hi>Relief</hi> of their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour's Neceſſities, there they do moſt commonly <hi>fight</hi> againſt God with ſuch their ſuperfluities. For we took notice juſt now, that God does <hi>not</hi> by the Law of Love and Charity take away <hi>any</hi> thing from our <hi>Neceſſaries;</hi> that he does very ſeldom, and in ſome <hi>rare</hi> Caſes only pare away any thing by it from our Conveniencies; and that therefore, generally ſpeaking, the Expences of our Charity is in a manner only charged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our <hi>ſuperfluities.</hi> Now it can be neither Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor Reaſon, nor Religion, that can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade or hinder Men from deducting a Charity out of their Superfluities. For all theſe three will of themſelves ſuggeſt to us, That what God
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102500:8"/>has given us over and above, and to ſpare, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond our <hi>own convenient</hi> Supplies, cannot be better imployed than for the <hi>neceſſary</hi> Supplies of <hi>other</hi> people. It muſt be then ſomething <hi>elſe;</hi> and not only ſo, but alſo ſomething that is <hi>contrary</hi> to Nature, Reaſon, and Religion, that muſt perſwade people to divert their Superflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties from ſo Noble and Beneficial an Uſe. And then, if we ſtill go on, and enquire what that ſomething is; the Iſſue of the Enquiry will be, That it muſt be Vice and Wickedneſs. For no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but that can ever perſwade people to Act counter to Religion, Reaſon, and Nature. Now though this ſin be <hi>ſometimes</hi> Covetouſneſs, yet it is not <hi>always</hi> ſo; nay, it is not ſo for the <hi>moſt</hi> part. For many times when <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> is the means to <hi>rake</hi> Superfluities together; Yet even then <hi>Luxury, Pride, Wantonneſs,</hi> and <hi>Debauchery</hi> ſhall be the <hi>End</hi> of ſuch means. But be it one, or be it t'other; that is, let Men be Niggards of their Superfluities, either to gratify the <hi>cloſer</hi> Sin of <hi>Covetouſneſs,</hi> or the <hi>looſer</hi> Sins of <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Dehauchery;</hi> yet in both Caſes they do not only withhold thoſe Superfluities from their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitous <hi>Brethren,</hi> and ſo ſin againſt God's Law of Love and Charity; But they do over and above directly employ them againſt God <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> and ſo do by them cheriſh and foment that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102500:8"/>his enemy, which his Soul abhors, and that is Sin. For <hi>Covetouſneſs,</hi> as the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5. <hi>is Idolatry.</hi> And though Uncharitableneſs, barely as <hi>ſuch,</hi> does break <hi>one</hi> of God's Laws; yet when <hi>accompanied</hi> with Idolatry, it <hi>renounces</hi> his <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>Government;</hi> that is, it thruſts him out of his Throne, and ſets up another in his ſtead. And ſo, on the other ſide, when a man withholds his Superfluities from his neceſſitous Brother, that he may lay them out upon his <hi>Luſts,</hi> he does not barely <hi>divert</hi> them <hi>from</hi> that Uſe, which God <hi>deſigns;</hi> but he does alſo <hi>pervert</hi> them to that Uſe which God <hi>forbids:</hi> He does by them not only not <hi>cheriſh</hi> God's <hi>friends,</hi> but he does alſo <hi>abet</hi> his <hi>enemies;</hi> and to make the crime look blacker ſtill, he does by them abet the enemy of <hi>him,</hi> from whom alone he <hi>receives</hi> them.</p>
            <p>And if this Crime be ſo heinous; Then what ſhall we ſay of the Sin of thoſe Men who em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy their Wealth, Power, Intereſt, or Parts, for the <hi>oppreſſing</hi> and <hi>injuring</hi> of thoſe very People, for whoſe <hi>Relief</hi> and <hi>Comfort</hi> the Abundance of ſuch things was beſtow'd on them by God. Certainly as this Sin is <hi>directed</hi> point-blank againſt the <hi>deſign</hi> of ſuch his <hi>Donation;</hi> ſo the <hi>guilt</hi> of it muſt needs be <hi>enhanced</hi> and <hi>aggravated</hi> by ſuch its <hi>direction.</hi> For it does, in effect, turn
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102500:9"/>Bread into Poiſon; and ſo makes the Means of Life to become the Inſtrument of Death. Which ought to be well conſidered by all wealthy and potent Oppreſſors; who, when God ſhall call them to it, will give but a very ill Account of their Stewardſhip: becauſe, when he ſhall take the matter into his own hand, (as he does all along in his Word aſſure us he will) their <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting</hi> his <hi>deſigns</hi> of <hi>Mercy</hi> will give an <hi>Edge</hi> to the Executions of his <hi>Juſtice;</hi> and they ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have Judgment without Mercy, becauſe they turned the means of Mercy into thoſe of Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Cruelty.</p>
            <p>And thus I have in general laid before you our Obligations to Charity, taken from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of God's general Grant, by which he gave the Earth to Man indefinitely; that is, to one Man, as well as another, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to every Man; and from his Law of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> by which he makes good his gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Grant to every Man in <hi>particular,</hi> though the Diſtributions of his Providence are ſo unequal, that ſome Men obtain no ſhare in it by ſuch diſtributions. For I thought it proper, Firſt to acquaint you under what <hi>Obligations</hi> you are, to be <hi>Charitable,</hi> before I offer'd you any <hi>Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> to <hi>Conduct</hi> your Charity: For we ſhall be the more willing to <hi>learn</hi> how to <hi>practiſe</hi> any Duty,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102500:9"/>when once we are <hi>convinced,</hi> that the <hi>practice</hi> of ſuch Duty is <hi>Neceſſary.</hi> And I cannot but hope, that you will ſtill the more diligently at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to, and the more carefully practiſe the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions which are to follow, when I have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted you, That I received them from a <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> Hand, and that upon that account they are the more likely to be pertinent to the Buſineſs of the <hi>Day,</hi> and ſo the more proper to direct that Charitable Deſign, which is the Occaſion of the preſent Solemnity.</p>
            <p>The Inſtructions then, which are to follow, may (as I conceive) be ranged under Two Heads.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Such as concern thoſe who <hi>Receive</hi> the Charity, and <hi>Enjoy</hi> the <hi>Benefit</hi> of the ſeveral Hoſpitals: And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Such who <hi>Manage</hi> ſuch Charity.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Firſt,</hi> They who Receive the Charity and enjoy the Benefit of the ſeveral Hoſpitals, ought,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To Praiſe God, the Author and Giver of all Good Things, who has made Proviſion for <hi>their</hi> Neceſſities and Conveniencies in a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary way, than he has for <hi>others</hi> their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Creatures. For ſome of thoſe others, are forced to Toil and Labour to <hi>gain</hi> the <hi>Poſſeſſion</hi> of what they <hi>want,</hi> before they can poſſibly <hi>enjoy</hi> what they want; and ſo their <hi>Labuor wears</hi> away
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102500:10"/>as much of their Strength and Life, as the <hi>Fruits</hi> of their Labour do <hi>Maintain;</hi> that is, they <hi>Labour</hi> and <hi>Toil</hi> that they may <hi>Live;</hi> and they <hi>Live</hi> that they may <hi>Toil</hi> and <hi>Labour:</hi> ſo that though they Live by the <hi>Bounty</hi> of God, yet they do not Live without their <hi>own</hi> Care and Labour beſides. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as moſt of thoſe people who ſubſiſt by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpital-Charities, have the <hi>Benefit</hi> of their Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance without either the Care or Labour of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding</hi> ſuch Maintenance: For you cannot but know, that the Poor of Four Hoſpitals in the Five, are in a manner wholly exempt from all ſuch Labour and Care. By which means it comes to paſs, that they who <hi>are</hi> in the <hi>greateſt Want,</hi> are at leſs trouble to <hi>ſupply</hi> ſuch their Wants, than thoſe that have the greateſt Wealth: and an Hoſpital-Lazar is exempt from all thoſe Cares which attend the Houſe-keeping of every <hi>Dives</hi> whatſoever. The thing has in it matter of ſome wonder, that people ſhould live at more Eaſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>other</hi> Mens Eſtates, than other Men do upon their <hi>own.</hi> But ſuch Wonders God can and has brought to paſs; <hi>Deus illis huc otia fecit.</hi> And upon this account it becomes their more eſpecial Duty to Praiſe God for his Bounty and Mercy to them. And this their Duty is to be particulariz'd in the next place, by their praiſing him for their Founders and Benefactors, and the Faithful Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtees,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102500:10"/>Executors and Adminiſtrators of either; of whom therefore they ought to <hi>entertain</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Thoughts,</hi> and (as occaſion offers it ſelf) to <hi>make</hi> Honourable <hi>mention.</hi> For though all Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings whatſoever do originally come from <hi>God;</hi> yet he is pleaſed to ſingle out ſome Perſons more <hi>eſpecially,</hi> and in ſome <hi>ſignal</hi> Caſes, whom he makes the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of Conveying ſuch his Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings to <hi>Men:</hi> And which is more and more to our purpoſe, to thoſe, whom he employs as ſuch his <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> he does not only <hi>allow</hi> but <hi>require</hi> an Honour to be paid in its due proportion, as well as to <hi>Himſelf.</hi> Thus becauſe our being is his <hi>Firſt</hi> and <hi>great</hi> Bleſſing to us, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which we ſhould not be in a capacity of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving any other Bleſſing from him; and becauſe he does by our Parents beſtow this great Bleſſing upon us; therefore he does, and that too by his Law, require, that we pay the Firſt and greateſt <hi>Honour</hi> to our <hi>Parents:</hi> And therefore we know, that in thoſe Laws of his, which concern our Duty to Mankind, he has Allotted the <hi>Firſt</hi> place to that Duty and Honour which we <hi>owe</hi> to our <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</hi> And as our <hi>Firſt</hi> Duty is owing to our <hi>Parents,</hi> becauſe from them we receive the <hi>Firſt</hi> and greateſt <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> our <hi>Being;</hi> ſo the <hi>next</hi> Duty is owing to ſuch our Benefactors by whoſe Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty we Subſiſt; that is, to <hi>whoſe</hi> Bounty we owe the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102500:11"/>
               <hi>Continuation</hi> and <hi>Preſervation</hi> of our Being. All thoſe therefore, who are partakers of the Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Hoſpitals, are bound to Praiſe God for their Founders and Benefactors, becauſe by their Bounty their Being is preſerved and continued. And if I might be allowed to offer my Directions in the Caſe, I ſhould think it adviſable, That the Governours of each Hoſpital ſhould ſet apart ſome Days, or at leaſt One in every Year, in in which all the Poor in their Reſpective Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, which are able ſo to do, ſhould be bound under ſome Penalty to be Preſent at a publick and ſolemn <hi>Commemoration,</hi> (more particularly of the Founders King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th and King <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th) and at leaſt at a general Thankſgiving offered up in Devout Praiſes for them and all their other Benefactors.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Thirdly,</hi> as thoſe, who are partakers of the Hoſpital-Charities ought to <hi>Praiſe</hi> God for their Founders and Benefactors, whether <hi>Dead</hi> or <hi>Alive;</hi> ſo ought they to <hi>Pray</hi> for <hi>ſuch</hi> their Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors and Governours which are <hi>now Living.</hi> For ſince their condition is ſuch, that they can make no <hi>other</hi> requital to the <hi>one</hi> for their <hi>Bounty,</hi> nor to the <hi>other</hi> for their <hi>Love, Labour,</hi> and <hi>Care;</hi> they ought at leaſt to recommend the <hi>Recompence</hi> of ſuch Bounty, Labour, and Care, to the Throne of the <hi>Divine</hi> Grace; that he who has put
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102500:11"/>it in their Hearts to do <hi>him</hi> a Service ſo Beneficial to <hi>themſelves,</hi> may by their Devotions be engaged to <hi>Reward</hi> ſuch their Service by his Gracious Hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Foruthly,</hi> As they who are partakers of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpital Charities ſhould praiſe God with their <hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Lips</hi> for ſuch his Mercy; ſo ought they alſo to do it with their <hi>Lives.</hi> For they who ſubſiſt by <hi>other</hi> Peoples Obedience to Gods Laws (as they moſt certainly do who Subſiſt by other Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Charities) are for that Reaſon obliged in an extraordinary Meaſure not to break God Laws <hi>themſelves:</hi> And ſince if others had not <hi>obſerved</hi> his <hi>Commands,</hi> they themſelves muſt have Periſhed for want of Maintenance; It is but Juſt and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitable if they do Periſh when they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>neglect</hi> his <hi>Commands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shall I add here, That even Benefactors and Governours themſelves ought in all the Inſtances hitherto mentioned to join with the reſpective Poor in Praiſing God for the ſeveral Founders and Benefactors? For we all ought to Praiſe God for Good and Pious Examples: They are good means of Grace, and lively Incentives to the like Pious and Religious Duties; And they ought to praiſe God for what is Beneficial to their <hi>Souls,</hi> as much as the <hi>Poor</hi> ought to praiſe him for what is Beneficial to their <hi>Bodies.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:102500:12"/>
            <p> One thing more I ſhall here add, and then ſhall proceed:</p>
            <p>And that is this: I have here laid down the Duties of the Poor, who are partakers of the ſeveral Charities. Now perhaps, though what I have ſaid in the Caſe <hi>has</hi> been but <hi>little;</hi> yet it may therefore be thought <hi>too much,</hi> becauſe moſt of thoſe Poor whom the Duties do concern, are <hi>not</hi> preſent; and ſo the Directions and Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations offered may be thought to be thrown away. But though they are <hi>not moſt</hi> of them here; yet I am well aſſured, that <hi>they</hi> that have the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Inſpection over them, <hi>are.</hi> And then I need but add, That as it is the Duty of the <hi>Poor</hi> to do what has been <hi>Taught;</hi> ſo it is the Duty of their <hi>Governours</hi> to take <hi>Care</hi> that they <hi>ſo</hi> do. And I muſt add, that this God expects of you, and that therefore this is part of the Charge that you have taken upon you; and therefore <hi>cannot,</hi> I am ſure, <hi>ought</hi> not to be neglected by you. For they who take care to Relieve Men's <hi>Bodies,</hi> have by that means alone a mighty Power put into their hands of <hi>regulating</hi> their <hi>Manners;</hi> becauſe they may bind them up to ſuch a regulation by that Natural, Strong, and Mighty Tye, the love of themſelves.</p>
            <p>And ſo I have done with my Firſt Directions, that is Directions to thoſe who are Partkers of the Charities.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:102500:12"/>
            <p> The Second fort of Directions follow, which concern thoſe who take care of the Admiſtration of ſuch Charities.</p>
            <p>And ſuch Directions are of Two ſorts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Such as concern the Governours of all the Hoſpitals in <hi>General.</hi> And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Such as concern the Reſpective Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of Each <hi>Particular</hi> Hoſpital.</p>
            <p>The Directions which concern the Governours of all the Hoſpitals in <hi>General,</hi> I ſhall from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions that I have received in the Caſe, lay down in the following Order.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Firſt,</hi> It will become every Governour to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf well of the <hi>End</hi> and <hi>Deſign</hi> to which <hi>that</hi> Hoſpital, of which he is Governour, was at Firſt <hi>Directed</hi> and <hi>Intended.</hi> For he who keeps his Eye directed to his End, will be the leſs likely to miſs his <hi>way</hi> to ſuch End. Now the beſt way to gain ſuch Information, will be to make himſelf acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the <hi>Charter</hi> of his Hoſpital, and with the <hi>Practices</hi> of the Firſt Governours in perſuance of ſuch Charter. For the <hi>Founders</hi> are in reaſon to be ſuppoſed to <hi>know</hi> their own Deſigns beſt; and their <hi>Charters</hi> are in reaſon to be ſuppoſed beſt to <hi>expreſs</hi> ſuch their Knowledg; and the <hi>Practiſes</hi> of the <hi>Firſt</hi> Governours are in reaſon to be ſuppoſed to be moſt <hi>Plain</hi> and <hi>Simple,</hi> and to come up <hi>cloſeſt</hi> to the Charters.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:102500:13"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It would become every Governour to have a particular and Hearty Affection to <hi>that</hi> ſort of Charity, whoſe Management and Care he takes upon him by being made a Governour. To this purpoſe a Charitable Man would do well to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine his Heart, to what ſort of Charity the Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Compaſſion do moſtly and chiefly lead him. For ſome People are more tenderly touched by the tender Age, and helpleſs Innocence of young Children: Others have a more ſenſible Compun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for the Pains, Wants, and Miſerable Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sick, Impotent, and Maimed; ſome Men have a great Averſation to Idleneſs; and ſome an Horror and Deteſtation to Vice and Debauchery. Other ſuch like Inclinations might be Named, but theſe anſwer beſt to our preſent Purpoſe, and the Time will not allow us to be Superfluous. To our Purpoſe then: Common Senſe will tell us, that a <hi>Zeal</hi> againſt <hi>Vice</hi> and <hi>Idleneſs</hi> will beſt qualify a Man (whenever he has a fair occaſion offer'd him) to endeavour to Reclaim ſuch People who are <hi>guilty</hi> of them; and that therefore he is the <hi>more</hi> likely to make a <hi>good</hi> Governour in <hi>that</hi> Hoſpital which is deſigned for that purpoſe. For every Man will pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue that deſign with an <hi>Hearty</hi> Zeal, to which his <hi>peculiar</hi> and <hi>Natural Inclinations</hi> lead him; and in ſuch a Caſe he will hardly grow weary in Well-doing. And he, who can <hi>deſign</hi> Good, and <hi>do</hi> Good,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102500:13"/>and <hi>Perſevere</hi> in ſo doing, is the likelieſt Man in Nature to bring the Good, he does, to Perfection. I muſt add (for I ſpeak to Chriſtians) That as he is the moſt likely to do it in <hi>Nature,</hi> ſo in ſuch his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings he is ſure to have the gracious <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> of the God of Nature: and then when a Man is animated to the proſecution of his Pious Enterpriſe, not only by his <hi>Inclinations</hi> but by his <hi>Faith,</hi> we may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe our ſelves as much ſecurity of Succeſs, as can in any Caſe be expected from Humane Undertakings.</p>
            <p>And therefore, if every Governour had an hearty Affection for the Charity of that Hoſpital to which he belongs, we might here break off, for there would be no need of farther Directions. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are all Men, and all Men have their Fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; therefore let me add in the</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Third</hi> Place, That it would become every Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour to remember now and then, that he is a Governour, and that by being ſo, he is engaged in ſuch buſineſs which concerns his Government. For a Governour of an Hoſpital (whatever may be thought by ſome Men to the contrary) is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than a mere Title. The Care is great, for ſo is the Family that is to be cared for: And every Man who has a ſhare in the <hi>Honour,</hi> (for all Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritabe Undertakeings are Honourable) ſhould have his ſhare in the <hi>Burthen</hi> to. Not that I think, that every Governour is to attend every buſineſs of his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102500:14"/>Hoſpital: That would hinder his own Buſineſs and the buſineſs of the Charity too; For moſt Buſineſſes are rather retarded than put forward by the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Managers. But <hi>thus</hi> much Diligence I think may be truly reckon'd the Duty of every Governour, That whenever the Common Prudence ſhall Diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute or Allot ſeveral Buſineſſes to ſeveral Combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Governours, each Governour ought ſo far to concern himſelf in that Buſineſs which falls with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Lot, as to take care that it do not Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry by his Default; and this he ought ſo much the rather to do, if he have antecedently given his Conſent to be charged among others, or ſingly and by himſelf, with ſuch Buſineſs. And I therefore add his own Conſent, becauſe as I am ſatisfied that the generality of any Set of Governours will not without his own conſent Imperiouſly Impoſe any Buſineſs upon any <hi>one</hi> or <hi>more</hi> of their Brethren; ſo I am loath to believe, that any Governour will wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully decline any Buſineſs that ſhall be propoſed to his Care and Management, without offering ſome plauſible, or at beſt probable Excuſe for ſuch his Refuſal. And (if I may be permitted to offer my opinion in the Caſe) I muſt freely confeſs, that I think it not only <hi>Commendable,</hi> but <hi>Juſt,</hi> that that Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour who frequently <hi>Refuſes</hi> to concern himſelf in the buſineſſes of the Charity, or who in a manner conſtantly Abſents himſelf from ſuch Buſineſs; I
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102500:14"/>ſay, I think, that ſuch a Governour ought of his own accord to make a compenſation to the <hi>Charity,</hi> by the <hi>Bounty</hi> of his <hi>Purſe</hi> for the <hi>Neglect</hi> of his <hi>Care:</hi> For <hi>Bounty</hi> promotes the end and deſign of the Charity, as well as <hi>Induſtry:</hi> And as the Charity would be <hi>thrown</hi> away, if there were none to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage</hi> it; ſo there would be no <hi>Charity</hi> to be <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged,</hi> if there were none to <hi>Beſtow</hi> it. I do not pretend to compare the Two ſorts of Charity. They are both in their Kind Noble and Great, and there is ſuch a thing as a Labour of Love, as well as a Bounty of Charity. And I know very well, that God has conſtantly raiſed up ſome Noble Spirits among you, who have Honourably diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged <hi>both</hi> Charities. But this, I think, I may adventure to ſay, That he who takes care neither of the <hi>one</hi> Charity, nor the <hi>other,</hi> does in <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianity Forfeit</hi> the Title of a Governour, though he may ſtill <hi>Retain</hi> it by the <hi>Candor</hi> of thoſe who really are ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It does become every Governour to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the Truſt (which he has taken upon him by accepting the Title and Office of a Governour) with <hi>ſincerity.</hi> That is, no man under the pretence of Charity, ſhould cover any ſelf or ſiniſter Deſign that may be prejucial to that <hi>Charity</hi> in <hi>particular,</hi> or to <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>common Honeſty</hi> in <hi>general.</hi> For it is poſſible that a man may <hi>pretend</hi> to aſſiſt the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102500:15"/>when his aim all the while is only to advantage <hi>himſelf:</hi> And it is poſſible, that a man may <hi>really promote</hi> the Charity, by being injurious and uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable to other <hi>men.</hi> But as I <hi>do</hi> not, ſo I wiſh I <hi>could</hi> not offer any Inſtances to make it good, that ſuch practices as theſe are more than poſſibilities. But every man's own heart can beſt acquaint him with his own ſincerity. However, becauſe the heart is deceitful above all things, it may prove a good means to ſecure your ſincerity, if you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to your imitation <hi>ſuch</hi> the Practices of your Predeceſſors, or Cotemporaries, as by a general Conſent have obtained the approbation of Good and Wiſe men, and whoſe Memories will always be preſerved freſh and ſweet in ſuch Regiſters which ſhall convey them down to Poſterity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Becauſe we are all mortal (but it is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped that the Hoſpitals are not ſo); therefore it will become you, the <hi>preſent</hi> Governours to take care, that the Charities ſhall never want ſuch Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours; and the way to make ſuch your Care ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, is by a continual choice of <hi>New</hi> Governors. For an everlaſting <hi>ſucceſſion</hi> of <hi>more</hi> and other Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors will be equivalent to an everlaſting <hi>continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> of the <hi>preſent:</hi> And they who chuſe good and proper Men to take care of the future manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Charities, do by ſo doing lay up ſuch a ſtock of Proviſions for thoſe Charities, which
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:102500:15"/>will laſt after they themſelves are dead and gone: And ſo your good Works will follow you for your <hi>own</hi> comfort, and yet ſtay <hi>behind</hi> you for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the <hi>Poor.</hi> Now what Perſons you ought to <hi>chuſe,</hi> you may beſt know by knowing what Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons you ought to be <hi>your ſelves:</hi> And therefore while I have offered you Inſtructions in the <hi>one</hi> caſe, I may well be underſtood to have done ſo in <hi>both:</hi> And ſo ſhall add no more in this Place, but only, That I am informed, and I am ſure it is fit that you ſhould be ſo too, That by Ancient Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, (though of late years grown out of uſe) the Governours of the Hoſpitals uſed to be choſen An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually upon St. <hi>Matthew's day.</hi> And certainly it muſt be ſome great and ſolemn Buſineſs, upon which the Governours of <hi>all</hi> the Hoſpitals ſhould this Day meet <hi>together;</hi> and it ſeems probable, that that Worthy Gentleman Mr. <hi>John Bankes</hi> (whoſe Name we mention with honour and reſpect) did make an Annual proviſion for Prayers, for a Sermon, and for the Attendance of the Church-Officers, that ſo ſo great a Work might not be undertaken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pious Devotions, and pious Inſtructions; the one to beg God's bleſſings upon you; the other to give Inſtructions to you for your faithful and pious Performance of ſuch Work.</p>
            <p>And truly the buſineſs of managing ſo great and extenſive Charity being great and weighty, it will
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102500:16"/>be neceſſary that your circumſpection in making choice of fit men for the doing of ſuch Buſineſs, be great and ſerious. For they who ſhall be truly thought fit for the diſcharge of ſo great a Truſt, muſt be (as my Inſtructions do very well word it (Men of Sincerity, Diligence, Unintereſtedneſs, Charity, Reputation, Leiſure <hi>for,</hi> and particular Affection <hi>to</hi> the Publick and Pious Deſigns of the Reſpective Inſtitutions.</p>
            <p>I ſhould now proceed to the next thing propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and that is, To offer ſome hings which do more particularly concern the Reſpective Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of the ſeveral Hoſpitals. Under which Head I ſhould have attempted to ſet forth to the full value the ſeveral Ends of the ſeveral Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. But I find that the Inſtructions given me are too large for a ſingle Diſcourſe; And I muſt not by the tediouſneſs of my Directions prevent your doing of thoſe very things to which I do direct you.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:102500:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
